Guide to the Wallace Earle Stegner papers: concerning the Asian-American Literary Exchange, 1949-1954
Department of Special Collections
Stegner, Wallace Earle Papers: concerning the Asian-American Literary Exchange,
1949-1954
M0807
2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Wallace Stegner, in an effort to promote good relations and literary exchanges between Asia and the United States, visited the Far East. With funding provided by the Rockefeller Foundation, Stegner and his wife visited India, Japan, the Philippines and Thailand between November 1950 and February 1951. After returning to Stanford, Stegner set up an informal literary agency devoted to placing Asian writings in U.S. publications. From 195 1-1954, he solicited manuscripts from Asian writers and translators and sent them to various magazines and publishers.
Administrative Information
Access
None.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Estate of Wallace Stegner, 1992
Provenance
Gift of the Estate of Wallace Stegner, 1992
Collection Scope and Content Summary
This collection includes the correspondence of Stegner and the various authors, editors and publishers he met on his trip, as well as letters from others who later heard of his project. There is also a great deal of correspondence with American editors and publishers, with whom Stegner sought to place Asian manuscripts. A few of Stegner's own manuscripts, written on Asian topics, are also included in the collection.
As far as possible, the collection follows the organization of the original files. Most of the papers, therefore, are filed under the relevant country name. Under the title of "Japan," for example, one can find correspondence with Japanese authors and publishers, clippings from the Japanese press, and so on.
Outgoing letters from Stegner are filed amongst related correspondence. For example, the file labeled "India: Publishers" includes both letters from the publishers and Stegner's responses. Most of Stegner's outgoing letters were written by his secretaries.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Narayan, R.K.; Vaidya, Suresh.; Kiyooka, Elichi.; Hiramatsu, Mikio.; Gonzalez, N.V.M.; Ray, Sri Annada Sankar.; Asian-American literary exchange.; Indic literature--20th century.; Japanese literature--20th century.; Philippine literature--English--20th century.; Thai literature--20th century.
Collection Contents
- American Book Publishers Council (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Asian Press Service (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Book exchange lists (Box 1, Folder 3)
- China: authors (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Copyrights and royalties (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Dead File" (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Expenses (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Expenses (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Expenses (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Expenses (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Egypt (Box 1, Folder 11)
- India: articles (Box 1, Folder 12)
- India: authors (A-C) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- India: authors (D-I) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- India: authors (K-N) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- India: authors (O-Q) (Box 1, Folder 16)
- India: authors (R-Z) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- India: Bose, Buddhavdeva (Box 1, Folder 18)
- India: correspondence (Box 1, Folder 19)
- India: correspondence (Box 1, Folder 20)
- India: correspondence (Box 1, Folder 21)
- India: Indian Institute of Culture (Box 1, Folder 22)
- India: magazines (Box 1, Folder 23)
- India: miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 24)
- India: notes (Box 1, Folder 25)
- India: notes (Box 1, Folder 26)
- India: press clippings (Box 1, Folder 27)
- India: publishers (Box 1, Folder 28)
- India: "Publisher's Exhibition" pamphlet (Box 1, Folder 29)
- India: P.E.N. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- India: Ray, Lila and Sri Annada Sankar (Box 1, Folder 31)
- India: R.K. Narayan (Box 1, Folder 32)
- India: Vaidya, Suresh ("A Literary Letter from India") (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Indonesia (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Indonesia: authors (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Intercultural Publications, Inc. (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Intercultural Publications, Inc. 1952 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Intercultural Publications, Inc. 1953 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Intercultural Publications, Inc. 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Japan: articles (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Japan: correspondence (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Japan: correspondence (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Japan: Keio University (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Japan: Kiyooka, Elichi (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Japan: Hiramatsu, Mikio n.d.-1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Japan: Kiyooka, Elichi (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Japan: Hiramatsu, Mikio 1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Japan: Kiyooka, Elichi (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Japan: Hiramatsu, Mikio (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Japan: Kiyooka, Elichi (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Japan: Hiramatsu, Mikio (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Japan: Hokuseido Press (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Japan: Kenkyusha Ltd. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Japan: military permits (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Japan: miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Japan: notebooks (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Japan: notebooks (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Japan: P.E.N. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Japan: Perkins, P.D. and Tone (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Japan: press clippings (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Japan: press clippings (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Japan: publishers (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Japan: translators (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Japan: translators (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Japan: translators (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Japan: translators (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Japan: translators (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Japan: translators (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Japan: translators (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Korea (Box 2, Folder 28)
- memorabilia (Box 2, Folder 29)
- "Packet libraries" for Asian universities (Box 2, Folder 30)
- "Packet libraries" booklists (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Phillipines: articles and notes (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Phillipines: authors (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Phillipines: authors (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Phillipines: authors (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Phillipines: authors (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Phillipines: Gonzalez, N.V.M. 1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Phillipines: Gonzalez, N.V.M 1951 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Phillipines: Gonzalez, N.V.M 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Phillipines: Gonzalez, N.V.M ("Children of the Ash-covered Loam") (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Phillipines: Gonzalez, N.V.M ("Lupa and the River") (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Poetry Magazine, Asian issue: correspondence 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Poetry Magazine, Asian issue: correspondence Jan 1953-Apr 1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Poetry Magazine, Asian issue: correspondence May 1953-June 1953 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Poetry Magazine, Asian issue: correspondence Aug 1953-Dec 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Poetry Magazine, Asian issue: manuscripts (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Poetry Magazine, Asian issue: manuscripts (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Rockefeller Foundation n.d. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Rockefeller Foundation 1949 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Rockefeller Foundation 1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Rockefeller Foundation 1951 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Rockefeller Foundation - 1952 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Rockefeller Foundation Jan 1953-June 1953 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Rockefeller Foundation July 1953-Dec 1953 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Stegner: essay correspondence (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Stegner: essays (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Stegner: essays (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Stegner: essays (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Stegner: notes (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Stegner: notes (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Thailand: correspondence (Box 3, Folder 25)
- travel arrangements (Box 3, Folder 26)
- UNESCO (Box 3, Folder 27)
- United States: authors (Box 3, Folder 28)
- United States: correspondence (Box 3, Folder 29)
- United States: correspondence (Box 3, Folder 30)
- United States: correspondence (Box 3, Folder 31)
- United States: correspondence (Box 3, Folder 32)
- United States: magazines (Box 3, Folder 33)
- United States: magazines (Box 3, Folder 34)
- United States: magazines (Box 3, Folder 35)
- United States: P.E.N. (Box 3, Folder 36)
- United States: publishers (Box 3, Folder 37)
- United States: State Dept. and Foreign Service (Box 3, Folder 38)
- "Verse from Asia" (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Clippings (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Ford Foundation (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Ford Foundation (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Ford Foundation (Box 4, Folder 4)
- India: Chulalongkorn University book request (Box 4, Folder 5)
- India: notes (Box 4, Folder 6)
- India: Osmania University (Box 4, Folder 7)
- India: P.E.N. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- India: Ray, Sri Annada Sankar ("The Book of Binu") (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Japan: authors (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Japan: authors (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Japan: authors (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Japan: authors (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Japan: authors (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Japan: notes (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Japan: Ozaki, Kazuo ("Insects of Various Kinds") and Hiroo Mukai (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Phillipines: Mano, Toribia (Box 4, Folder 17)